有时候  我觉得我被诅咒了
Sometimes, I think I'm cursed.
因为一些在我出生之前发生的事
Because of something that happened before I was even born.
很久以前  有这么一家人
See, a long time ago, there was this family.
爸爸是一个音乐家
The papa, he was a musician.
他和他的家人一起唱歌跳舞  过得很幸福
He and his family would sing and dance and count their blessings.
可是爸爸有个梦想  要唱歌给全世界听
But he also had a dream. To play for the world.
有一天
And one day,
他背着他的吉他离开了  再也没有回来
he left with his guitar and never returned.
而妈妈
And the mama...
她没时间为爸爸的离开而伤心难过
She didn't have time to cry over that walk-away musician.
抛弃了生命中所有的音乐后
After banishing all music from her life
她想了个办法继续养活自己的女儿
she found a way to provide for her daughter.
她卷起了袖子  学习怎么做鞋子
She rolled up her sleeves and she learned to make shoes.
她明明可以学做糖果
She could have made candy,
或者烟花  或者给摔跤手穿的闪亮裤子
or fireworks, or sparkly underwear for wrestlers,
但是不  她偏偏选了鞋子
but no, she chose shoes.
后来她教女儿怎么做鞋子
Then she taught her daughter to make shoes.
然后又教会了她的女婿
And later, she taught her son-in-law.
她的孙辈也不例外
Then her grandkids got roped in.
随着家族日渐壮大  生意也越做越大
As her family grew, so did the business.
音乐曾经让她的家族分崩离析
Music had torn her family apart.
但是鞋子又帮她建家立业
But shoes held them all together.
那个女人
You see, that woman
就是我的曾曾奶奶  伊美黛
was my great-great-grandmother, Mama Imelda.
我出生之前很久她就死了
She died way before I was born.
但是每年亡灵节  我们家
But my family still tells her story
还是会讲她的故事
every year on Dia de los Muertos...
这是纪念逝者的节日
the Day of the Dead.
她的小女儿
And her little girl,
就是我的曾祖母  可可曾奶奶
she's my great-grandmother, Mama Coco.
你好  可可曾奶奶
Hola, Mama Coco.
你好吗  胡里奥
How are you, Julio?
其实我的名字叫米格尔
Actually, my name is Miguel.
可可曾奶奶记性不太好了
Mama Coco has trouble remembering things.
但是我还是很喜欢和她聊天
But it's good to talk to her anyway.
我几乎所有事都和她说
So, I tell her pretty much everything.
我以前这样跑步
I used to run like this.
但现在我这样跑步快多了
But now I run like this which is way faster.
胜利者是  超级无敌的可可曾奶奶
And the winner is Luchadora Coco!
我这边有个酒窝  这边没有
I have a dimple on this side, but not on this side.
有酒窝没酒窝  有酒窝没酒窝
Dimple, no dimple. Dimple, no dimple.
米格尔  好好吃你的
Miguel, eat your food.
我的奶奶  她是可可曾奶奶的女儿
My abuelita, she's Mama Coco's daughter.
你太瘦了  孩子  多吃点
Oh, you're a twig, mijo. Have some more.
不用了  谢谢
No, gracias.
我问过你要不要再来点玉米粉蒸肉
I asked if you would like more tamales!
好吧
Sí?
我记得你就是这么说的
That's what I thought you said!
奶奶和伊美黛老祖宗
Abuelita runs our house
当年一样管理这个家族
just like Mama Imelda did.
不准有音乐
No music!
我觉得我们是墨西哥唯一一个
I think we're the only family in Mexico
讨厌音乐的家族
who hates music.
我的家人觉得无所谓  但是我...
And my family's fine with that. But me...
-午餐之前回来  孩子  -爱你  妈妈
- Be back by lunch, mijo. - Love you, Mama.
我和我其他家人不一样
I am not like the rest of my family!
-你好  米格尔  -你好
- Hola, Miguel! - Hola!
-非常感谢  -不客气  米格尔
- Muchas gracias. - De nada, Miguel.
但丁
Hey! Dante!
起来  趴下  打滚  握手[抖动]
Sit. Down. Roll over. Shake.
击拳
Fist bump!
好样的  但丁
Good boy, Dante!
我知道我不该喜欢音乐
I know I'm not supposed to love music.
但这不是我的错  是他的错
But it's not my fault! It's his!
埃内斯托·德拉库斯
Ernesto de la Cruz.
有史以来最伟大的音乐家
The greatest musician of all time.
在这个广场上
Right here in this very plaza,
埃内斯托·德拉库斯向着成为墨西哥历史上
Ernesto de la Cruz took his first steps...
最伟大的歌手  迈出了第一步
toward becoming the most beloved singer in Mexican history.
他一开始是个圣塔塞西莉亚的无名小卒  像我一样
He started out a total nobody from Santa Cecilia, like me.
但是当他开始唱歌  人们就爱上了他
But when he played music, he made people fall in love with him.
他参演过电影
He starred in movies.
他有最炫酷的吉他  他能飞
He had the coolest guitar! He could fly!
他写了很多首很棒的歌
And he wrote the best songs.
埃内斯托
埃内斯托·德拉库斯
德拉库斯
请记住我
但是我一直以来最喜欢的是...
But my all-time favorite, it's...
埃内斯托·德拉库斯
请记住我
Remember me
虽然再见必须说
Though I have to say goodbye
-请记住我  -请记住我
- Remember me - Remember me
眼泪不要坠落
Don't let it make you cry
我虽然要离你远去
For even if I'm far away
你住在我心底
I hold you in my heart
在每个分离的夜里
I sing a secret song to you
为你唱一首歌
Each night we are apart
请记住我
Remember me
虽然我要去远方
Though I have to travel far
请记住我
Remember me
当听见吉他的悲伤
Each time you hear a sad guitar
这就是我跟你在一起唯一的凭据
Know that I'm with you the only way that I can be
直到我再次拥抱你
Until you're in my arms again
他过着人人梦寐以求的生活
He lived the kind of life you dream about.
请记住我
Remember me
直到1942年
Until 1942.
他被一个大钟砸死了
When he was crushed by a giant bell.
我想变得和他一样
I want to be just like him.
有时候  我看着德拉库斯
Sometimes, I look at De la Cruz
冥冥之中感觉我们有着某种联系
and I get this feeling like we're connected.
好像如果他能成为音乐家  也许有一天我也能
Like if he could play music, maybe someday, I could too.
要是我的家人不阻挠就好了
If it wasn't for my family.
小伙子
Ay-ay-ay, muchacho.
我要你擦鞋  没想听你的人生故事
I asked for a shoe shine not your life story.
对不起
Oh, yeah. Sorry.
我只是在家里没法说这些话  所以...
I just can't really talk about any of this at home. So...
如果我是你
If I were you,
我就冲回家和我的家人们说...
I'd march right up to my family and say...
"我就是个音乐家  接受吧"
"Hey, I'm a musician. Deal with it."
我可绝对说不出口
I could never say that.
你在搞音乐吧
You are a musician, no?
我不知道算不算
I don't know.
我是说  我只唱给自己听过
I mean, I only really play for myself.
德拉库斯是因为隐藏了自己的才华  才成为
Ah! Did De la Cruz become the world's best musician
世界上最棒的音乐家吗
by hiding his skills?
不  他走向广场
No! He walked out onto that plaza
大声演唱给大家听
and he played out loud.
你看  他们在布置今晚的场地了
Mira, Mira, they're setting up for tonight!
亡灵节音乐比赛
The music competition for Dia de Muertos.
亡灵节才艺大赛
中央广场  晚上七点
你想和你的偶像一样吗  去报名吧
You want to be like your hero? You should sign up!
我的家人会气疯了的
Uh-uh. My family would freak!
如果你害怕  那就乖乖做鞋子吧
Look, if you're too scared then, well, have fun making shoes.
别这样  德拉库斯经常怎么说的来着
Come on, what did De la Cruz always say?
抓住你的机遇
Seize your moment?
让我看看你的本事  小伙子
Show me what you got, muchacho.
我来做你第一个观众
I'll be your first audience.
米格尔
Miguel!
-奶奶  -你在干什么
- Abuelita! - What are you doing here?
离我孙子远一点
You leave my grandson alone.
太太  别紧张
Dona, please!
我只是在擦鞋
I was just getting a shine.
我很清楚你的把戏  臭乐手  他和你说了什么
I know your tricks, mariachi. What did he say to you?
他只是在给我看他的吉他
He was just showing me his guitar.
真不要脸
Shame on you.
我的孙子是个纯洁可爱的小天使
My grandson is a sweet little Angelito Querido Cielito.
他不需要你的音乐  臭乐手
He wants no part of your music, mariachi.
你离他远一点
You keep away from him.
可怜的小家伙  没事了  孩子
Ay, pobrecito. Oh, estas bien, mijo.
你知道你不该来这种地方
You know better than to be here in this place!
你赶紧给我回家
You will come home. Now.
我们和你说了多少遍了
How many times have we told you?
那个广场上全是臭乐手
That plaza is crawling with mariachis.
知道了  叔叔
Yes, Tio Berto.
-不不不不不  -走开  走开
- No, no, no, no, no! - Ah! Go away, you. Go!
那是但丁
It's just Dante.
不要给流浪狗起名字
Never name a street dog.
这样它们会一直跟着你  去捡我的鞋子
They'll follow you forever. Now, go get my shoe.
里维拉家族鞋店
我在乐手广场找到了你们儿子
I found your son in Mariachi Plaza.
米格尔
Ay, Miguel!
你知道奶奶不喜欢那个广场
You know how Abuelita feels about the plaza.
我只是在擦鞋子
I was just shining shoes.
一个音乐家的鞋子
A musician's shoes!
但那个广场上有很多鞋可以擦
But the plaza's where all the foot traffic is.
如果奶奶说不许去广场  那就不许去广场
If Abuelita says no more plaza, then no more plaza.
-但是那今晚呢  -今晚怎么了
- But what about tonight? - What's tonight?
他们要举办一个才艺大赛
Well, they're having this talent show.
我想能不能...
And I thought I might...
-报名吗  -也许吧
- Sign up? - Well, maybe?
你得有才艺才能参加才艺大赛
You have to have talent to be in a talent show.
你打算表演什么  擦鞋吗
What are you gonna do? Shine shoes?
今晚是亡灵节
It's Dia de los Muertos.
谁都不该出门  今晚应该家族团聚
No one's going anywhere. Tonight is about family.
灵坛  我们走
Ofrenda room. Vamonos.
别这样看我
Don't give me that look.
我们的祖先每年只有亡灵节的晚上
Dia de los Muertos is the one night of the year
才能来看我们
our ancestors can come visit us.
我们将他们的照片供奉在灵坛上
We've put their photos on the ofrenda
他们的灵魂才能够过来
so their spirits can cross over.
这可是非常重要的事
That is very important.
如果我们不放照片  他们就来不了
If we don't put them up, they can't come.
我们做了这些吃的
We made all this food,
放上这些他们生前喜欢的东西  孩子
set out the things they loved in life, mijo.
都是为了让他们能回来一家团聚
All this work to bring the family together.
我不希望你随便乱跑
I don't want you sneaking off to who knows where.
你去哪里
Where are you going?
我以为你说完了
I thought we were done.
天啊  我们都是这个家的一份子
Ay, Dios mio. Being part of this family means
就是要和家人待在一起
being here for this family.
我不希望你最后和...
I don't want to see you end up like...
可可曾奶奶的爸爸一样吗
Like Mama Coco's papa?
不要提那个男人  最好把他忘掉
Never mention that man! He's better off forgotten.
但是你先提...
But you're the one who...
我只是...
I was just...
但是...我...
But... I...
爸爸  爸爸回来了吗
Papa? Papa is home?
妈妈  没事的  没事了
Mama, calmese, calmese.
爸爸回来了吗
Papa is coming home?
不  妈妈  没事的  我在呢
No, Mama. It's okay. I'm here.
你是谁
Who are you?
休息一下吧  妈妈
Rest, Mama.
我对你严厉是因为我关心你  米格尔
I'm hard on you because I care, Miguel.
米格尔  米格尔
Miguel? Miguel?
我们该拿这个孩子怎么办
What are we going to do with that boy?
你说得对  他就需要这个
You're right. That's just what he needs.
里维拉家族鞋店
是你啊  快进来
It's you. Get in here.
快点  但丁  快进来
Come on, Dante. Hurry up!
你会给我惹麻烦的  伙计
You're gonna get me in trouble, boy.
会被人听到的
Someone could hear me.
真希望真的有人想听我演奏
I wish someone wanted to hear me.
除了你  好吧
Other than you. Ew. Okay.
完美
Perfecto!
德拉库斯精选
我必须要唱歌  我必须要演奏
I have to sing. I have to play!
音乐不仅仅只在我心中  音乐是我的生命
The music, it's not just in me, it is me.
当生活让我失望  我弹起我的吉他
When life gets me down, I play my guitar.
这世界也许自有它的规则
The rest of the world may follow the rules,
但我必须遵从我的内心
but I must follow my heart.
你知道那种感觉  空气中都有歌声
You know that feeling like there's a song in the air and...
只为你而演奏
it's playing just for you?
这感觉如此贴近
A feeling so close...
你仿若触手可及
You could reach out and touch it
我从未想过
I never knew
会有如此热忱渴望
I could want something so much
可它真切存在
but it's true
你得有信心  修女
You must have faith, sister.
但神父他不会听我的
Oh, but, Padre, he will never listen.
他会听得进音乐
He will listen. To music.
唯有歌声
Only a song
拥有改变心意的力量
Has the power to change a heart
永远不要低估音乐的力量
Never underestimate the power of music.
但神父不会允许的
But my father, he will never give his permission.
我受够了要请求别人的允许
I am done asking permission.
当你的机会到来时  你绝不能与它擦肩而过
When you see your moment, you mustn't let it pass you by.
你必须抓住机遇
You must seize it!
德拉库斯先生
Senor de la Cruz,
为了抓住机遇您都做了些什么
what did it take for you to seize your moment?
我必须坚信我的梦想
I had to have faith in my dream.
没有人会将成功送到我面前
No one was going to hand it to me.
我必须靠自己的努力去追求梦想
It was up to me to reach for that dream.
-决不放弃  让梦想成真  -让梦想成真
- Grab it tight and make it come true. - and make it come true.
亡灵节才艺大赛
再也不躲躲藏藏  但丁  我必须抓住我的机遇
No more hiding, Dante. I got to seize my moment!
我一定要去乐师广场表演
I'm gonna play in Mariachi Plaza if it kills me.
亡灵节开始了
Dia de los Muertos has begun!
不不  我们得洒出一条路来
No, no. We have to make a clear path.
花瓣会指引着我们的先人回家
The petals guide our ancestors home.
我们可不想让他们的亡灵迷路了
We don't want their spirits to get lost.
我们想要他们回来
We want them to come and enjoy all the food
享受祭坛上的美酒佳肴
and drinks on the ofrenda.
妈妈
Mama!
这张桌子要放在哪里
Where should we put this table?
放在院子里  孩子
In the courtyard, mijos.
你想让它挨着厨房吗
You want it down by the kitchen?
对  挨着另一张桌子
Si. Next to the other one.
-藏到下面去  到下面去  -米格尔
- Get under! Get under! - Miguel?
没什么  妈妈  爸爸  我...
Nothing! Mama, Papa. I...
米格尔  你奶奶想出了一个非常棒的主意
Miguel, your abuelita had the most wonderful idea.
我们都决定了  是时候让你来店里工作了
We've all decided. It's time you joined us in the workshop!
-什么  -以后不用再擦鞋了
- What? - No more shining shoes.
你可以做鞋了  每天放学回来就做
You'll be making them every day after school.
我们的小小米格尔
Oh! Our Migueli-ti-ti-ti-to
即将延续家族传统
carrying on the family tradition.
还是在亡灵节这一天
And on Dia de los Muertos!
老祖宗们会非常骄傲的
Your ancestors will be so proud.
你可以像维多利亚姨婆一样编织凉鞋
You'll craft huaraches just like your Tia Victoria.
像你的胡里奥爷爷一样做翼尖皮鞋
And wingtips like your Papa Julio.
万一我做不好怎么办
But what if I'm no good at making shoes?
米格尔  你的家人都在这指导你呢
Ah, Miguel. You have your family here to guide you.
你是里维拉家的人  而里维拉家的人
You are a Rivera. And a Rivera is...
天生就是鞋匠  世代传承
A shoemaker. Through and through.
这才是我儿子  贝托
That's my boy! Berto!
开瓶好酒  我要庆祝一下
Break out the good stuff. I want to make a toast.
但丁  不  但丁  停下
Dante! No, Dante. Stop!
不不不不不
No, no, no, no, no! No.
德拉库斯的吉他
De la Cruz's guitar?
爸爸  爸爸
Papa? Papa?
可可曾奶奶  你爸是埃内斯托·德拉库斯吗
Mama Coco, is your papa Ernesto de la Cruz?
爸爸  爸爸
Papa! Papa!
爸爸  爸爸  就是他
Papa! Papa! It's him!
我知道我的曾曾爷爷是谁了
I know who my great-great-grandfather was.
米格尔  从那上面下来
Miguel, get down from there.
可可曾奶奶的爸爸是埃内斯托·德拉库斯
Mama Coco's father was Ernesto de la Cruz!
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
我会成为一个音乐家
I'm gonna be a musician!
这些都是什么
What is all this?
你瞒着自己的家人做了这种事
You keep secrets from your own family?
都是因为他在广场上待的时间太多了
It's all that time he spends in the plaza.
让他脑袋里装满了疯狂的幻想
Fills his head with crazy fantasies.
这才不是幻想
It's not a fantasy.
这个人是埃内斯托·德拉库斯
That man was Ernesto de la Cruz!
历史上最伟大的音乐家
The greatest musician of all time!
我们不认识这个人
We've never known anything about this man!
但无论他是谁  他都抛弃了他的家庭
But whoever he was, he still abandoned his family.
你学他坏样不会有任何前途
This is no future for my son.
但爸爸  你说我的家人会指引我
But, Papa, you said my family would guide me.
德拉库斯也是我的家人
Well, De la Cruz is my family.
我就应该玩音乐
I'm supposed to play music.
休想  那个人的音乐是种诅咒
Never! That man's music was a curse.
我不会允许的
I will not allow it.
-只要您让我...  -米格尔...
- If you would just let... - Miguel...
你得听你家人的话
You will listen to your family.
别再碰音乐
No more music.
-你们听我弹一次就好  -没得商量
- Just listen to me play! - End of argument.
你想和那个男人下场一样吗  被遗忘
You want to end up like that man? Forgotten?
照片上不了家里的灵坛
Left off your family's ofrenda?
我才不在乎自己有没有被什么愚蠢的灵坛供奉
I don't care if I'm on some stupid ofrenda.
-不  -妈妈
- No! - Mama!
就这样  没有吉他  没有音乐
There. No guitar. No music.
好了  和家人吃个饭这事儿就翻篇了
Oh, come. You'll feel better after you eat with your family.
我不想再待在这个家了
I don't want to be in this family!
米格尔  米格尔
Miguel! Miguel!
亡灵节才艺大赛
我想像德拉库斯一样在广场上表演
I want to play in the plaza, like De la Cruz.
我还能报名吗
Can I still sign up?
你有乐器吗
You got an instrument?
没有  但要是我能借把吉他...
No. But if I can borrow a guitar...
参赛的音乐人得自备乐器
Musicians got to bring their own instruments.
孩子  找把吉他来
You find a guitar, kid,
我就帮你报名
I'll put you on the list.
-我能借你的吉他吗  -抱歉  小伙子
- Can I borrow your guitar? - Sorry, muchacho.
-你们有多余的吉他吗  -没有
- You guys have a spare guitar? - No.
我想借下吉他  就一小会儿
I need a guitar just for a little bit.
走开  孩子
Get out of here, kid.
曾曾爷爷  我该怎么办
Great-great-grandfather, what am I supposed to do?
抓住机遇
不不不
No, no, no, no.
但丁  停下  闭嘴
Dante, stop! Callate! Shh!
对不起
I'm sorry.
德拉库斯先生  请不要生气
Senor De la Cruz, please don't be mad.
我是米格尔
I'm Miguel.
您的曾曾孙子  我得借这把吉他
Your great-great grandson. I need to borrow this.
我们的家人觉得音乐是种诅咒
Our family thinks music is a curse.
他们都不理解我  但我知道你能理解
None of them understand but I know you would have.
你会让我跟从自己的内心
You would have told me to follow my heart.
抓住我的机遇
To seize my moment!
如果你同意的话
So, if it's all right with you,
我要去广场上表演  就像你一样
I'm gonna play in the plaza. Just like you did!
那把吉他不见了
The guitar! It's gone!
有人偷了德拉库斯的吉他
Somebody stole De la Cruz's guitar!
窗户破了  看
The window's broken. Look!
是谁  谁在里面
All right, who's in there?
抱歉  事情不是看上去那样
I'm sorry. It's not what it looks like.
德拉库斯是我的...
De la Cruz is my...
里面没有人
There's nobody here.
-米格尔  -妈妈
- Miguel! - Mama!
米格尔  回家吧  你在哪  米格尔
Miguel, come home. Where are you, Miguel?
天啊  孩子  你还好吗
Dios mio! Little boy. Are you okay?
来  我拉你一把
Here. Let me help you.
谢谢  我...
Thanks. I...
你怎么回事
Do you mind? Whoa!
看看她长多大了
Look how big she's getting.
但丁  你能看到我吗
Dante! You can see me?
等等  发生什么了  但丁
Wait! What's going on? Dante!
-对不起  对不起  -米格尔
- Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry. - Miguel?
-米格尔  -米格尔
- Miguel? - Miguel?
你怎么来了  你怎么在这里  你还能看到我们
You're here? Here, here. And you can see us?
我们的小小米格尔
Our Migueli-ti-ti-ti-to!
请问我怎么会认识你
Remind me how I know you.
我们是你的家人  孩子
We're your family, mijo.
-罗西塔姑婆  -对
- Tia Rosita? - Si.
-胡里奥爷爷  -你好
- Papa Julio? - Hola.
维多利亚姨婆
Tia Victoria?
他看起来还没死透
He doesn't seem entirely dead.
也不像还活着
He's not quite alive either.
我们得找到老祖宗伊美黛  她知道如何解决
We need Mama Imelda. She'll know how to fix this.
老祖宗伊美黛出事了
Oye! It's Mama Imelda.
她过不来
She couldn't cross over.
-她被卡住了  -卡在了另一边
- She's stuck! - On the other side!
奥斯卡叔公  菲利普叔公
Tio Oscar? Tio Felipe?
你好  米格尔
Hey, Miguel.
我感觉这可能和你有关
I have a feeling this has something to do with you.
但如果老祖宗伊美黛没法来找我们...
But if Mama Imelda can't come to us...
我们就去找她  出发
Then we are going to her. Vamonos!
走吧  米格尔  没关系的
Come on, Miguel. It's okay.
但丁  但丁  但丁等等
Dante? Dante! Dante, wait up!
你得和我待着  孩子  我们不知道...这是哪里
You got to stay with me, boy. We don't know... where...
这不是一场梦  你们真的就住在这个地方
This isn't a dream then. You're all really out there.
-你觉得我们不存在吗  -我也不知道
- You thought we weren't? - Well, I don't know.
我还以为那可能是
I thought it might've been one of those
大人编来骗小孩子的
made up things that adults tell kids.
就像维生素一样
Like vitamins.
米格尔  维生素真的存在
Miguel, vitamins are a real thing.
现在我有点相信了
Well, now I'm thinking maybe they could be.
宝贝  你这样盯着别人可不太礼貌...
Mija, it's not nice to stare at...
我的天啊
Ay! Santa Maria!
那些是爱波瑞吉吗  但它们是...
Are those... Alebrijes! But those are...
真的爱波瑞吉  灵兽
Real alebrijes. Spirit creatures.
它们会给亡灵引路
They guide souls on their journey.
小心脚下  它们到处便便
Watch your step. They make caquitas everywhere.
欢迎回到亡灵之国
Welcome back to the Land of the Dead.
请准备好回返需要申报的物品
Please have all offerings ready for re-entry.
回返
欢迎回来  有要申报的东西吗
Welcome back. Anything to declare?
几根小油条  家人送来的
Some churros. From my family.
好好享用  下一位
How wonderful. Next.
如果您在出入关时遇到问题
If you are experiencing travel issues,
家人团聚署的工作人员
agents at the Department of Family Reunions
将竭诚协助您
are available to assist you.
有请下一家
Next family, please.
两位的照片摆在你们儿子的灵坛上
Your photos are on your son's ofrenda.
旅途愉快
Have a great visit.
谢谢
Gracias.
谨记在日出前回来
And remember to return before sunrise.
旅途愉快
Enjoy your visit.
下一位
Next.
您的照片在您牙医的灵坛上  祝旅途愉快
Your photo's on your dentist's ofrenda. Enjoy your visit.
-谢谢  -下一位
- Gracias. - Next?
对  是我  弗里达·卡罗
Yes! It is I. Frida Kahlo.
我们能不能跳过扫描这一步
Shall we skip the scanner?
摆我的灵坛太多  你的小机器会挂掉
I'm on so many ofrendas it'll just overwhelm your blinky thingy.
糟糕  好像没人摆你的照片  弗瑞达
Well, shoot, looks like no one put up your photo, Frida.
好吧  我刚说自己是弗里达  我撒谎了
Okay, when I said I was Frida, just now, that was a lie.
我为自己的行为道歉
And I apologize for doing that.
灵坛上没照片就没有过桥权
No photo on an ofrenda, no crossing the bridge.
我就悄悄溜过去  你都不会知道我走了
I'm just gonna zip right over. You won't even know I'm gone.
马上到了  就差一点点
Almost... there. Just a little further.
起来吧你
Upsy-daisy...
行  好吧  谁在乎啊  臭花瓣桥
Fine. Okay. Fine, who cares? Dumb flower bridge!
要是没人摆我的照片我都不知道该怎么办
I don't know what I'd do if no one put up my photo.
-下一位  -过来孩子  轮到我们了
- Next? - Oh! Come, mijo. It's our turn.
欢迎回来  朋友们  有要申报的东西吗
Welcome back, amigos. Anything to declare?
事实上还真有
As a matter of fact, yes.
你好
Hola.
呼叫玛尔塔·冈萨雷斯-拉莫斯
Paging Marta Gonzales-Ramos.
请上报给第七级人员
Please report to Level Seven.
我想念我的鼻子
I miss my nose.
拜托了  帮帮忙  朋友
Come on, help us out, amigo.
我们今晚还有十几个灵坛要赶
We got to get to a dozen ofrendas tonight.
我们不去你前妻家过节
We are not visiting your ex-wife's family for Dia de Muertos!
要你们管事的出来
I demand to speak to the person in charge!
很抱歉  夫人  系统显示没人供奉你的照片
I'm sorry, senora, it says here no one put up your photo.
我家人肯定会在灵坛上摆我的照片的
My family always puts my photo on the ofrenda.
这个邪恶的盒子谎话连篇
That devil box tells you nothing but lies!
-老祖宗伊美黛  -我的亲人
- Mama Imelda? - Oh, mi familia!
他们不让我过桥
They wouldn't let me cross the bridge.
告诉这个女人和这个邪恶的盒子
Tell this woman and her devil box
灵坛上放了我的照片
that my photo is on the ofrenda.
我们还没来得及去灵坛
Well, we never made it to the ofrenda.
-什么  -我们遇见了
- What? - We ran into...
-米格尔  -伊美黛曾奶奶
- Miguel? - Mama Imelda.
怎么回事
What is going on?
你们是里维拉一家人吗
You the Rivera family?
你们被诅咒了
Well, you're cursed.
什么
What?
亡灵节是向死者供奉的节日
Dia de los Muertos is the night to give to the dead.
你反倒偷走了死者的东西
You stole from the dead!
我不是要偷走那把吉他
But I wasn't stealing the guitar.
吉他
Guitar?
那把吉他是我曾曾爷爷的东西
It was my great-great-grandfather's.
他肯定也愿意借给我的
He would have wanted me to have it.
我们家不准提那个搞音乐的
We do not speak of that musician.
他对我们家来说已经死了
He is dead to this family.
你们都已经死了
You're all dead.
不好意思  这是谁家的爱波瑞吉
I am sorry. Whose alebrije is that?
它叫但丁
That's just Dante.
它看起来一点也不像爱波瑞吉
He sure doesn't look like an alebrije.
它看上去只是一只普通的老狗
He just looks like a plain old dog.
或是谁丢在理发店的香肠
Or a sausage someone dropped in a barbershop.
不管是什么  都让我严重过敏
Whatever he is, I am terribly allergic.
可是但丁身上又没有毛
But Dante doesn't have any hair.
我没有鼻子  还不是一样会过敏
And I don't have a nose, and yet, here we are.
但都不能解释我为什么不能过桥
But none of this explains why I couldn't cross over.
你把我的照片从灵台上拿下来了
You took my photo off the ofrenda?
-我不是有意的  -我们怎么才能把他送回去
- It was an accident! - How do we send him back?
既然只是家庭矛盾
Well, since it's a family matter...
解除家族诅咒的方法就是
the way to undo a family curse
-接受家人的祝福  -这样就行了吗
- is to get your family's blessing. - That's it?
接受家人的祝福
Get your family's blessing
一切就能恢复正常了
and everything should go back to normal.
但必须赶在日出之前
But you got to do it by sunrise.
日出后会怎么样
What happens at sunrise?
天呐  你的手
Hijole! Your hand!
米格尔  你可不能在我们面前晕倒了
Whoa, Miguel, can't have you fainting on us.
别担心  你的家人就在这
But not to worry. Your family's here.
你现在就可以接受家人的祝福了
You can get your blessing right now.
万寿菊  万寿菊  不好意思  夫人
Cempasuchil, cempasuchil. Aha! Perdon, senora.
你看着这个孩子说出他的名字
Now, you look at the living and say his name.
米格尔
Miguel.
成了  然后说"我给你我的祝福"
Nailed it. Now say, "I give you my blessing."
我给你我的祝福
I give you my blessing.
我给你我的祝福  让你回到家
I give you my blessing to go home...
把我的照片放在灵坛上
to put my photo back on the ofrenda,
再也别碰音乐了
and to never play music again.
什么  她不能这样
What? She can't do that!
理论上说  她可以加上任何她希望的条件
Well, technically, she can add any condition she wants.
好吧
Fine.
然后你把花瓣交给米格尔
Then you hand the petal to Miguel.
没有骷髅了
No skeletons!
乐师广场  我来了
Mariachi Plaza, here I come.
这才过两秒你就违反承诺了
Two seconds and you already break your promise.
这不公平  这是我的人生
This isn't fair. It's my life.
你的人生已经过完了
You already had yours.
胡里奥爷爷  我需要你的祝福
Papa Julio, I ask for your blessing.
罗西塔姑奶  奥斯卡叔公
Tia Rosita? Oscar?
菲利普叔公  维多利亚姨奶
Felipe? Tia Victoria?
别为难我们了  孩子
Don't make this hard, mijo.
要么听我的回家要么就别回家了
You go home my way or no way.
你真的这么恨音乐吗
You really hate music that much?
我绝不会让你走上他那条路的
I will not let you go down the same path he did.
他那条路  他是家人
The same path he did. He's family.
听你伊美黛曾曾奶奶的话
Listen to your Mama Imelda.
她是为你好
She's just looking out for you.
你要听进去
Be reasonable.
对不起  我要去上个厕所
Con permiso, I need to visit the restroom.
马上就回来
Be right back.
我们是不是该告诉他
Should we tell him there are no restrooms
亡灵之地没有厕所
in the Land of the Dead?
我们走
Vamonos.
有一家人在找一个活人小男孩
We got a family looking for a living boy.
我想当个音乐家  就得得到音乐家的祝福
If I want to be a musician, I need a musician's blessing.
我们需要找到我的曾曾爷爷
We got to find my great-great-grandpa.
等等  小伙子
Hold it, muchacho.
我找到那个活人小男孩了
I found that living boy!
借过一下  借过一下  伙计们
Excuse me. Excuse me, folks.
借过一下
Excuse me.
不  不  但丁
No, no. Dante!
扰乱治安  涉嫌拒捕
Disturbing the peace. Fleeing an officer.
假扮一字眉
Falsifying a unibrow.
-这也犯法吗  -非常违法
- That's illegal? - Very illegal.
你需要洗心革面  朋友
You need to clean up your act, amigo.
朋友  很高兴你这样称呼我
Amigo? Oh, that's so nice to hear you say that
因为这个亡灵节我很不好过
because I have just had a really hard Dia de Muertos
现在真的很需要一个朋友
and I could really use an amigo right now.
朋友都会相互帮助
And amigos, they help their amigos.
你今晚放我过桥
You get me across that bridge tonight,
我绝对不会亏待你的
and I'll make it worth your while.
你喜欢德拉库斯吗  他和我是老交情了
You like De la Cruz? He and I go way back.
我能帮你弄到他光芒万丈演唱会的前排座位
I can get you front row seats to his Sunrise Spectacular show.
我还能带你进后台  你可以见到他本人
I'll get you backstage. You can meet him.
你只需要放我过桥
You just got to let me cross that bridge!
我应该把你关起来让你在牢里过节
I should lock you up for the rest of the holiday.
但我马上下班了  我也想见我活着的家人
But my shift's almost up and I want to visit my living family.
这次就只给你个警告好了
So I'm letting you off with a warning.
至少把我的戏服还给我吧
Can I at least get my costume back?
不行
No.
算什么朋友啊
Some amigo.
你真的认识德拉库斯吗
You really know De la Cruz?
谁想  天呐  你是个活人
Who wants to... Ahh! Ay! You're alive!
别出声  是的  我还活着
Shh! Yeah, I'm alive.
如果我想回到活人的世界
And if I want to get back to the Land of the Living...
就需要德拉库斯的祝福
I need De la Cruz's blessing.
为什么非要找他
That's weirdly specific.
他是我的曾曾爷爷
He's my great-great-grandfather.
他是你的曾曾...什么
He's your Gr... What?
等等  等等
Wait, wait, wait. Wait, wait.
等下  不  等等  等等
Wait. No, wait, wait, wait.
对了  你要回活人的世界
Yes! You're going back to the Land of the Living!
要不算了  或许这不是一个好主意
You know what? Maybe this isn't such a good...
不  不  孩子  孩子
No, no, nino! Nino, nino,
我能帮你  你也能帮我
I can help you. You can help me.
我们可以相互帮助
We can help each other.
但最重要的是  你能帮我
But most importantly, you can help me.
-米格尔  -我叫埃克托
- Miguel! - I'm Hector.
好
That's nice.
等等我  小子
Esperame, chamaco!
他会害死自己的
He is going to get himself killed.
该我的灵魂向导登场了  小南瓜
I need my spirit guide... Pepita.
米格尔碰过的花瓣在谁那
Who has that petal Miguel touched?
在这  可爱的爱波瑞吉
Here. Nice alebrije.
别动  往上看  一点点  向上看  上  上
Hold still. Look up. A ver, a ver. Look up, up, up.
这里  大功告成
Aqui arriba, eso... Eh, la rayita.
好了
Okay. Hey! Ta-da!
这下你死得透透的了
Dead as a doorknob.
听着  米格尔  这个地方靠回忆而存在
So listen, Miguel, this place runs on memories.
大家都记得你
When you're well remembered,
会把你的照片摆出来
people put up your photo
你就能通过那座桥
and you get to cross the bridge
在亡灵节时探望活着的亲人
and visit the living on Dia de Muertos.
除非像我这样
Unless you're me.
你不能过桥吗
You don't get to cross over?
没有人供奉我的照片
No one's ever put up my picture.
但你能改变这个现状
But you can change that!
这是你吗
This is you?
很帅吧
Mmuy guapo, eh?
所以  你带我去见我的曾曾爷爷
So, you get me to my great-great-grandpa...
我就回家后把你的照片摆上灵坛
then I put up your photo when I get home?
真聪明  对  真是个好主意  有个问题
Such a smart boy! Yes! Great idea, yes! One hiccup.
德拉库斯很难接近
De la Cruz is a tough guy to get to
而我需要立即过桥
and I need to cross the bridge soon.
今晚就要
Like, tonight.
所以  你在这还有别的家人吗
So, you got any other family here, you know?
比较  好接近一点的
Someone a bit more, eh, accessible?
没了
Nope.
别唬我  小伙子
Don't yank my chain, chamaco.
你在这肯定还有别的家人
You got to have some other family.
只有德拉库斯
Only De la Cruz.
要是你不能帮我  我就自己去找他
If you can't help me, I'll find him myself.
好  好  孩子  行  行
Okay. Okay, kid. Fine! Fine!
我带你去见你的曾曾爷爷
I'll get you to your great-great-grandpa.
没那么容易的  知道吗  他是个大忙人
It's not gonna be easy, you know? He's a busy man.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
我在学骷髅走路  融入大家
I'm walking like a skeleton. Blending in.
别  骷髅不这样走路
No. Skeletons don't walk like that.
-你就这么走路  -不  我没有  打住
- It's how you walk. - No, I don't! Stop it!
埃内斯托·德拉库斯光芒万丈演唱会
Ernesto De la Cruz's Sunrise Spectacular?
太酷了
Que padre!
每年你的曾曾爷爷都要举办这个白痴演唱会
Every year your great-great-grandpa puts on that dumb show...
作为亡灵节的谢幕演出
to mark the end of Dia de Muertos.
你能带我参加
And you can get us in!
你说了你有前排座位票的
Hey, you said you have front row tickets!
那是骗人的  我道歉
That... was a lie. I apologize for that.
冷静  孩子  好了  我会带你去见他的
Cool off, chamaco. Come on. I'll get you to him.
怎么去
How?
因为我正好知道他在哪彩排
Because I happen to know where he's rehearsing.
你最好把我的裙子带回来了  埃克托
You better have my dress, Hector.
你好  塞西
Hola, Ceci.
-你好  -塞西  我把裙子弄丢了
- Hola. - Ceci, I lost the dress.
我就知道
Ya lo sabia!
我在日出前要给四十名舞者打扮好
I got to dress forty dancers by sunrise.
多亏了你  现在少了一个扮弗里达的了
Thanks to you, I'm one Frida short of an opening number!
但丁  我们不该来这
Dante! We shouldn't be in here.
不  不  但丁  快过来
No, no, Dante! Ven aca!
你  你是怎么进来的
You! How did you get in here?
-我是跟着我的  -墨西哥无毛犬
- I just followed my... - Oh! The mighty Xolo dog!
给迷失的亡灵引路
Guider of wandering spirits.
你把谁的灵魂引到我这里来了
And whose spirit have you guided to me?
我觉得它不是灵魂向导
I don't think he's a spirit guide.
这个世界的爱波瑞吉有很多形态
The alebrijes of this world can take many forms.
它们既神秘又强大
They are as mysterious as they are powerful.
或许它只是条狗  来  我需要你帮我看看
Or maybe he's just a dog. Come, I need your eyes.
你当观众  关灯
You are the audience. Darkness.
黑暗中  出现了一个巨大的木瓜
And from the darkness, a giant papaya.
舞者从木瓜中爬出
Dancers emerge from the papaya,
这些舞者都是我
and the dancers are all me.
他们吸允着母亲的乳汁
And they go to drink from the milk of their mother,
一株仙人掌
who is a cactus.
仙人掌也是我
But who is also me.
乳汁并不是乳汁  而是泪水
And her milk is not milk but tears.
是不是太惹眼了
Is it too obvious?
我觉得恰到好处
I think it's just the right amount of obvious?
可以加点音乐  可不可以这样
It could use some music. Oh, what if you did like...
然后这样
Oh! And then it could go...
要是燃起熊熊火焰呢
And what if everything was on fire?
没错  火焰  熊熊火海
Yes! Fire! Everywhere!
太有创意了  你真有艺术家的天赋
Inspired! You have the spirit of an artist.
伴舞退场  音乐淡出  灯光渐灭
The dancers exit. The music fades, the lights go out.
然后埃内斯托·德拉库斯登台
And Ernesto de la Cruz rises to the stage!
他唱几首歌  太阳升起  观众欢呼
He does a couple of songs, the sun rises, everyone cheers...
请问一下  德拉库斯不在这吗
Excuse me, where's the real De la Cruz?
埃内斯托从不彩排
Ernesto doesn't do rehearsals!
他正忙着在那个塔顶办派对呢
He's too busy hosting that fancy party at the top of his tower.
小子  你怎么能在这乱跑
Chamaco, you can't run off on me like that.
走吧  别给人家添乱了
Come on, stop pestering the celebrities.
你说我的曾曾爷爷会在这
You said my great-great-grandpa would be here!
结果他在那头开什么派对
He's halfway across town throwing some big party.
这家伙居然连自己的彩排都不来
That bum. Who doesn't show up to his own rehearsal?
你们要真是好朋友
If you're such good friends,
他怎么没请你去
how come he didn't invite you?
你还是他曾曾孙子呢
He's your great-great-grandpa,
不也没请你去
how come he didn't invite you?
古斯塔沃  知道怎么才能去派对吗
Hey, Gustavo! You know anything about this party?
一票难求啊
It's the hot ticket!
他如果没请你的话
But if you're not on the guest list,
那就别做梦了 熏香肠
you're never getting in, Chorizo.
-快看  是熏香肠  -熏香肠
- Hey! It's Chorizo! -Choricito!
真好笑  真好笑
A-ha. Very funny, guys. Very funny.
熏香肠
Chorizo?
这家伙可有名了
Oh, this guy's famous!
快  问问他是怎么死的
Go on, go on. Ask him how he died.
我不想再提了
I don't want to talk about it.
他是吃香肠噎死的
He choked on some chorizo!
不是噎死  好吗
I didn't choke, okay?
是食物中毒  这两者区别可大了
I got food poisoning which is a big difference.
我讨厌这些搞音乐的人
This is why I don't like musicians.
一群自以为是的混蛋
Bunch of self-important jerks.
-我也搞音乐  -是吗
- Hey! I'm a musician! - You are?
你要真想见到埃内斯托的话
If you really want to get to Ernesto,
在德拉库斯广场
there is that music competition...
有一个音乐比赛
at the Plaza De la Cruz.
赢了就能去派对上表演
Winner gets to play at his party.
不行  小子  别犯傻了
No, no. Chamaco, you're loco if you think...
我必须得到我曾曾爷爷的祝福
I need to get my great-great-grandfather's blessing!
你能帮我弄把吉他吗
You know where I can get a guitar?
我认识个人
I know a guy.
找到了吗  小南瓜  找到他了吗
Have you found him, Pepita? Have you found our boy?
-有脚印  -我们家做的鞋
- A footprint! - It's a Rivera boot.
-7码的脚  -7码半
- Size seven! - And a half.
-内八字  -是米格尔
- Pronated. - Miguel.
你怎么会想当个音乐家
Why the heck would you want to be a musician?
我的曾曾爷爷就是音乐家
My great-great-grandpa was a musician!
一辈子都像耍猴一样
Who spent his life performing like a monkey
表演给陌生人看
for complete strangers.
还是算了吧  谢谢
No thank you. No! Guacala!
你懂什么
What do you know?
你说的吉他到底在哪里
So, how far is this guitar anyway?
快到了
We're almost there.
跟上  小子  来吧
Keep up, Chamaco. Come on.
-埃克托表哥  -你们好啊  姨父
- Cousin Hector! - Hey! These guys! Hey, Tio!
过得还好吗
Que onda?
他们都是你家人吗
These people are all your family?
算是吧  我们都没有照片和灵坛
In a way. We're all the ones with no photos or ofrendas.
无家可归  即将被遗忘  你懂吗
No family to go home to. Nearly forgotten, you know?
所以我们就互称表哥  姨父之类的
So, we all call each other cousin, or tio, or whatever.
-埃克托  -切珞姨妈
- Hector! - Tia Chelo!
谢谢你了
Muchas gracias!
给我留点  猪皮哥在吗
Hey! Save some for me! Is Chicharron around?
在那边的房间里
Eh, in the bungalow.
不知道他有没有心情见你
I don't know if he's in the mood for visitors.
谁会不想见我埃克托呢
Who doesn't like a visit from Cousin Hector?
晚上好  猪皮哥
Buenas noches, Chicharron!
别让我看到你那张蠢脸  埃克托
I don't want to see your stupid face, Hector.
好啦  现在可是亡灵节
Come on. It's Dia de Muertos.
我陪你喝两杯
I brought you a little offering.
-滚开  -马上  猪皮哥
- Get out of here. - I would, Cheech.
不过问题是  我和我的朋友米格尔
But the thing is, me and my friend, Miguel...
想借一下你的吉他
We really need to borrow your guitar.
-我的吉他  -是的
- My guitar? - Yes.
我心爱的宝贝吉他
My prized beloved guitar?
我保证马上就还你
I promise we'll bring it right back.
你之前说马上还我的小货车还没还我呢
Like the time you promised to bring back my van?
还有我的小冰箱
Or my mini-fridge?
-这个嘛  -我的手绢
- Ah, you see... - Or my good napkins?
我的绳套  我的大腿骨
My lasso? My femur?
这次不一样啦
Well, no, not like those times.
我的大腿骨呢  你这个
Where is my femur? You...
-没事吧  老兄  -我快消失了  埃克托
- You okay, amigo? - I'm fading, Hector.
我能感觉到
I can feel it.
连吉他都弹不动了
I couldn't even play that thing if I wanted to.
你弹给我听
You play me something.
不行  说好了再也不碰的  猪皮哥
No. You know I don't play anymore, Cheech.
我是帮这个孩子借的
The guitar is for the kid.
想要的话  凭本事拿
You want it, you got to earn it.
为你破次例吧  老兄
Ay, only for you, amigo.
想听点什么
Any requests?
我最喜欢的那首  你懂的
You know my favorite, Hector.
谁都知道胡安妮塔
Well, everyone knows Juanita
她瞳孔有两种颜色
Her eyes each a different color
龇牙裂嘴  面容憔悴
Her teeth stick out and her chin goes in
她的
And her...
原词为knockers  意为女人的乳房
手臂关节拖在地板上
Knuckles they drag on the floor
-你唱错词了吧  -有孩子在场呢
- Those aren't the words. - There are children present.
披头散发
Her hair is like a briar
站着总是两腿弯弯
She stands in a bow-legged stance
要不是我也长得抱歉
And if I weren't so ugly
她或许会对我中意
She'd possibly give me a chance
往事如风呀
Brings back memories.
谢了
Gracias.
等等  他怎么了
Wait. What happened?
彻底被遗忘了
He's been forgotten.
如果在活人世界里
When there's no one left in the living world
没人记得你的话
who remembers you...
就会从这里消失
you disappear from this world.
我们称之为最终的死亡
We call it the final death.
那他去哪里了呢
Where did he go?
没人知道
No one knows.
可我见过他  我回去后会记得他
But I've met him. I could remember him when I go back!
没用的  年轻人
No, it doesn't work like that, chamaco.
我们的过往  必须由那些
Our memories, they have to be passed down
我们生前认识的人
by those who knew us in life...
口口相传才管用
in the stories they tell about us.
记得猪皮哥的人都不在世了
But there's no one left alive to pass down Cheech's stories.
谁都有消失的一天
Hey, it happens to everyone eventually.
来吧  未来歌神  你还等着赢比赛呢
Come on, De la Cruzcito, you've got a contest to win.
你说你讨厌音乐家
You told me you hated musicians.
原来你也搞过音乐
You never said you were one.
不然我怎么认识你的曾曾爷爷
How do you think I knew your great-great-grandpa?
我们以前是搭档
We used to play music together.
是我教的他
Taught him everything he knows.
别吹牛了  你和埃内斯托·德拉库斯是搭档
No manches! You played with Ernesto De la Cruz...
他可是史上最伟大的音乐家
the greatest musician of all time?
你可真搞笑
Ah, you're funny.
史上最粗的眉毛还差不多
Greatest eyebrows of all time maybe.
他的音乐嘛  别提了
But his music? Eh, not so much.
你可别瞎说了
You don't know what you're talking about.
欢迎来到德拉库斯广场
Welcome to the Plaza De la Cruz!
露一手吧  小子
Showtime, Chamaco!
卖短袖啦  卖娃娃啦
Llevelo! T-shirts! Bobbleheads!
欢迎各位
Bienvenidos a todos!
准备好享用音乐盛宴了吗
Who's ready for some musica?
今晚有一场音乐比拼  朋友们
It's a battle of the bands, amigos.
赢家可以去塔顶的派对现场
The winner gets to play for the maestro himself,
为埃内斯托·德拉库斯
Ernesto de la Cruz...
演奏一曲
at his fiesta tonight!
这就是我们的入场券  小子
That's our ticket, muchacho.
比赛正式开始
Let the competition begin!
好了  你想好唱哪首了吗
So, what's the plan? What are you gonna play?
当然是《请记住我》
Definitely Remember Me.
不行  那首不行
No! Not that one. No.
这可是他最火的一首歌
Come on. It's his most popular song!
不行  有点太火了
Ah, it's too popular.
请记住我
Remember me
虽然我要去远方
Though I have to travel far
请记住我
Remember me
眼泪不要坠落
Don't let it make you cry
-那《有点疯狂》呢  -好主意  就这么定了
- What about Poco Loco? - Epa! Now that's a song!
未来歌神  你们准备
De la Cruzcito? You're on standby.
疯狂恰恰  你们下一组
Los Chachalacos, you're up next.
疯狂恰恰
Los Chachalacos!
你上台前都这么紧张吗
You always this nervous before a performance?
我不知道  以前从来没上过台
I don't know. I've never performed before.
什么  你不是说你是音乐家吗
What? You said you were a musician!
是啊  我是说  只要我赢了
I am! I mean, I will be.
我就是
Once I win.
你就这么打算的吗  不行  你必须赢
That's your plan? No. You have to win.
你能不能活过今晚全靠这次了
Your life literally depends on... you winning.
你却从没上过台
And you've never done this before!
我来替你
I'll go up there.
-不行  我必须得上去  -为什么
- No! I need to do this. - Why?
如果我一直这么怯场的话
If I can't go out and play one song,
怎么能自称音乐家
how can I call myself a musician?
这很重要吗
What does that matter?
我不只是想得到德拉库斯的祝福
Because I don't just want to get de la Cruz's blessing...
我想证明我配得上他的祝福
I need to prove that I'm worthy of it.
还真是感天动地
Oh, that's such a sweet sentiment
偏偏是现在
at such a bad time!
算了  算了  你想表演是吧
Okay! Okay. You want to perform?
那就好好表演
Then you got to perform!
首先你得放松  甩掉紧张
First, you have to loosen up. Shake off those nerves.
然后用尽全力仰天长啸
Now give me your best grito.
-仰天长啸  -对  喊一嗓子
- My best grito? - Come on, yell! Belt it out.
爽死了  轮到你了
Ah, it feels good. Okay, now you.
真的够了  小子
Oh, come on, kid.
未来歌神  该你上台了
De la Cruzcito, you're on now!
米格尔  看着我  看着我
Miguel, look at me. Hey, look at me.
你可以的
You can do this.
用你的音乐抓住他们的耳朵
Grab their attention and don't let it go.
好好唱  小子  你可以的
Make them listen, Chamaco. You've got this.
未来歌神
De la Cruzcito.
他在干什么  怎么不唱
What's he doing? Why isn't he playing?
让会唱歌的狗回来吧
Bring back the singing dogs!
好样的  快开始吧
Que bien! Vamonos! Whoo!
问天空什么色彩
What color is the sky
我的亲爱  我的亲爱
Ay mi amor, ay mi amor
你说它是红色
You tell me that it's red
我的亲爱  我的亲爱
Ay mi amor, ay mi amor
我把鞋放何处
Where should I put my shoes
我的亲爱  我的亲爱
Ay mi amor, ay mi amor
你说放在你的头上
You say put them on your head
我的亲爱  我的亲爱
Ay mi amor, ay mi amor
你令我有一点疯狂
You make me un poco loco
究竟这是怎么样
Un poqui-ti-ti-to loco
猜测并没有根据
The way you keep me guessing
我同意我也答应
I'm nodding and I'm yes-ing
我把这当做福气
I'll count it as a blessing
我不过是有一点疯狂
That I'm only un poco loco
别  别  别
No! No! No!
骷髅舞跳得不错嘛
Not bad for a dead guy!
你唱得也不错  小子
Not so bad yourself, gordito! Eso!
他就在附近  找到他
He's close! Find him!
这疯狂由你开始
The loco that you make me
这的确是疯狂无比
It is just un poco crazy
你真的非常无理
The sense that you're not making
你有权利不关心
The liberties you're taking
让我摇摇头叹息
Leaves my cabeza shaking
你就是有一点疯狂
You're just un poco loco
干得漂亮  小米格尔
Idale, duro, Miguelito
我们在找一个活人小男孩
We're looking for a living kid.
十二岁左右
About twelve?
你见过一个活人小男孩吗
Have you seen a living boy?
有一点   点  点  点  点  点  点  点
Un poqui-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-
点点点点点点疯狂
ti-ti-ti-to loco
干得好  我为你骄傲
You did good! I'm proud of you. Eso!
再来一个  再来一个
Otra! Otra! Otra!
-你要去哪儿  -我们得赶快走
- Hey! Where are you going? - We got to get out of here!
什么  你疯了吗  我们就要赢了
What? Are you crazy? We're about to win this thing.
女士们  先生们
Damas y caballeros,
插播一条紧急通知
I have an emergency announcement.
请留意一个活人小男孩
Please be on the lookout for a living boy.
他名叫米格尔
Answers to the name of Miguel.
今晚早些时候他从家人身边走失
Earlier tonight he ran away from his family.
他的家人希望送他回去活人的世界
They just want to send him back to the Land of the Living.
慢着
Wait, wait.
你告诉我德拉库斯是你唯一的家人
You said De la Cruz was your only family.
只有他才能送你回家
The only person who could send you home.
我的确有别的家人  但是...
I do have other family, but...
你一早就能把我的照片带回去
You could have taken my photo back this whole time?
可他们讨厌音乐  我需要音乐家的祝福
But they hate music! I need a musician's blessing.
-你骗了我  -你不也骗了我
- You lied to me! - Oh, you're one to talk.
看看我  我就快被遗忘了  米格尔
Look at me. I'm being forgotten, Miguel.
我都不知道能不能撑过今晚
I don't even know if I'm gonna last the night.
我绝对不能错过
I'm not gonna miss my one chance
我来之不易的过桥机会
to cross that bridge because...
就因为你荒唐的音乐梦
you want to live out some stupid musical fantasy.
一点都不荒唐
It's not stupid!
我带你去找你的家人
I'm taking you to your family.
-放开我  -你会感谢我的
- Let go of me! - You'll thank me later.
你根本不想帮我  你只关心你自己
You don't want to help me. You only care about yourself!
留着你的蠢照片吧  离我远点
Keep your dumb photo. Stay away from me!
不
No!
孩子  你去哪儿了
Hey, chamaco! Where did you go?
孩子  对不起  快回来
Chamaco! I'm sorry! Come back!
但丁 不要叫了  不  但丁  放开我
Dante, callate! No! Dante, stop it.
他帮不了我
He can't help me.
但丁  停下
Dante! Stop!
别这样  别跟着我了
Stop it! Leave me alone!
你不是亡灵向导  你只是只笨狗
You're not a spirit guide. You're just a dumb dog!
快走吧
Now get out of here!
-是他  -是那个活人小男孩
- It's him! - It's that living boy!
-我听说过他  快看  -他还活着
- I heard about him. Look! - He's alive!
-他还活着  -这个小男孩是活人
- He's alive. - The boy is alive!
这场闹剧该停止了  米格尔
This nonsense ends now, Miguel!
我现在就把祝福给你  送你回家
I am giving you my blessing and you are going home.
我不想要你的祝福
I don't want your blessing!
米格尔  站住
Miguel, stop!
回来
Come back!
米格尔
Miguel!
我是在救你的命
I am trying to save your life!
-你是在要我的命  -你说什么
- You're ruining my life! - What?
音乐是我唯一的快乐
Music's the only thing that makes me happy.
而你却要夺走我的快乐
And you want to take it away.
你永远不会明白的
You'll never understand.
虽然生活对我百般折磨  哭泣的女人
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
我也无法停止爱你
No dejare de quererte...
我以为你讨厌音乐
I thought you hated music.
我爱音乐  我还记得当时的感觉
Oh, I loved it! I remember that feeling...
我丈夫弹着吉他  我唱着歌
when my husband would play, and I would sing
仿佛一切都不重要了
and nothing else mattered.
但当我们有了可可
But when we had Coco,
我才突然发现生命中
suddenly there was something in my life that...
有比音乐更重要的东西
mattered more than music.
我想安定下来
I wanted to put down roots.
而他想唱歌给全世界听
He wanted to play for the world.
我们为了想要的生活  彼此都做出了牺牲
We each made a sacrifice to get what we wanted.
现在你必须也做出选择
Now you must make a choice.
可我不想做选择
But I don't want to pick sides!
为什么你就不能支持我呢
Why can't you be on my side?
一家人不应该就这样吗
That's what family's supposed to do.
彼此支持  你永远不会懂的
Support you. But you never will.
-祝您玩得愉快  -太激动了
- Have a good time. - Oh, how exciting!
是圣徒先生  我是您的粉丝  可以合张影吗
Oh, El Santo. I'm a big fan! You mind if I...
谢谢您  先生
Gracias, Senor.
-有邀请函吗  -我不需要那个
- Invitation? - It's okay.
我是埃内斯托的曾曾孙子
I'm Ernesto's great-great-grandson.
-打扰一下  先生们  -大伙儿  这是唱《有点疯狂》的那孩子
- Disculpen, senores... - Hey, guys! It's poco loco!
-你今晚的表演太棒了  -你们也是
- You were on fire tonight! - You too!
看在是同行的份上  帮我个忙行吗
Hey, musician to musician... I need a favor.
音乐大赛冠军  祝贺你们  请进
Oh, the competition winners. Congratulations, chicos.
多谢各位
Thanks, guys!
好好玩儿吧  小音乐家
Hey! Enjoy the party, little musico!
谢谢
Gracias!
看  那是埃内斯托
Look! It's Ernesto!
德拉库斯
De la Cruz!
德拉库斯先生
Senor de la Cruz!
借过  德拉库斯先生  德拉...
Pardon me! Senor De la Cruz! Senor De la...
当你的机会到来时
When you see your moment,
你绝不能与它擦肩而过
you mustn't let it pass you by.
你必须抓住机遇
You must seize it.
就快到了  但丁
We're almost there, Dante.
德拉库斯先生  德拉...
Senor De la Cruz! Senor De la...
我们又能怎么办呢  没有用的
But what can we do? It is hopeless...
你得有信心  修女
You must have faith, sister.
但神父他不会听我的
But Padre, he will never listen.
他会听得进音乐
He will listen... to music.
女士们和先生们  各位午安  各位晚安
Senoras y senores, buenas tardes, buenas noches
各位午安  各位晚安  女士们和先生们
Buenas tardes, buenas noches Senoritas y senores
在今夜跟你相遇  带给我满心的欢喜
To be here with you tonight Brings me joy! Que alegria
我用音乐代替言语
For this music is my language
这世界是个大家庭
And the world es mi familia
我用音乐代替言语
For this music is my language
这世界是个大家庭
And the world es mi familia
我用音乐代替言语
For this music is my language
这世界是个大家庭
And the world es mi familia
我用音乐代替言语
For this music is my lang...
你没事吧  孩子
Are you all right, nino?
是你  那个小男孩
It's you! You are that boy!
你就是那个从活人的世界来的小男孩
The one who came from the Land of the Living.
您...知道我
You... know about me?
人人都在说你的事
You are all anyone has been talking about.
你怎么到这儿来了
Why have you come here?
我叫米格尔  您的曾曾孙子
I'm Miguel. Your great-great-grandson.
我...有个曾曾孙子
I... have a great-great-grandson?
我需要您的祝福
I need your blessing
才能回家去  成为一个音乐家
so I can go back home and be a musician.
就像您一样
Just like you.
家里的其他人  他们都不支持我
The rest of our family, they wouldn't listen.
我希望您能支持我
But I hoped you would.
孩子  你有这般的天赋  我怎么会不支持呢
My boy, with a talent like yours, how could I not listen?
我有个曾曾孙子
I have a great-great-grandson!
-快看  是弗里达  -没错 是我 弗里达·卡罗
- Look! It's Frida! - Yes, it is I. Frida Kahlo.
-我的荣幸  女士  -谢谢
- It is an honor, Senora. - Gracias.
内格雷特  因方特
Hey, Negrete! Infante!
你们见过我的曾曾孙子没
Have you met my great-great-grandson?
这是我的曾曾孙子
My great-great-grandson.
他还活着  他是个小小音乐家
He's alive! And a musician to boot!
有酒窝没酒窝  有酒窝没酒窝
Dimple. No dimple. Dimple. No dimple.
没酒窝
No dimple!
敬我们的友谊
To our friendship.
我愿为你赴汤蹈火  我的朋友  干杯
I would move Heaven and Earth for you, mi amigo. Salud!
有毒
Poison!
你知道吗  我从不用替身演员
You know, I did all my own stunts.
虽然再见必须说  请记住我
Though I have to say goodbye Remember me...
这些都是我在活人世界的
All of this came from my amazing fans
众多歌迷送的
in the Land of the Living.
太多了  我都不知道该拿它们怎么办
They leave me more offerings than I know what to do with!
怎么了  一下子接受不了吗  你看起来有点迷茫
Hey, what's wrong? Is it too much? You look overwhelmed.
-没事  一切都很好  -那你是
- No! It's all great! - But?
只是
It's just...
只是我从小到大一直把您视为偶像
I have been looking up to you my whole life.
您在我心中无所不能
You're the guy who actually did it!
但是您有后悔过吗
But did you ever regret it?
为了音乐放弃了一切
Choosing music over everything else?
确实很艰难
It was hard.
告别家乡  独自上路
Saying goodbye to my hometown. Heading off on my own...
还离开了家人
Leaving your family?
是的  但若重来一次我还是会做同样的选择
Si. But I could not have done it differently.
这是命中注定的
One cannot deny who one is meant to be.
而你  我的曾曾孙子  命中注定要成为音乐家
And you, my great-great-grandson, are meant to be a musician!
你和我  米格尔  我们都是艺术家
You and I, we are artists, Miguel.
我们不能拘泥于小家
We cannot belong to one family.
整个世界都是我们的家
The world is our family.
开始放烟花了
The fireworks have begun!
再过一会儿  我的光芒万丈演唱会就要开始了
Soon the party will move across town for my Sunrise Spectacular.
米格尔  你一定要来
Miguel, you must come to the show!
你可以做我的特约嘉宾
You will be my guest of honor!
-你说真的吗  -当然了  孩子
- You mean it? - Of course, my boy.
可我去不了
I can't.
我得在日出前回到家里
I have to get home before sunrise.
对  我真得赶紧送你回家了
Oh! I really do need to get you home.
这是我的荣幸
It has been an honor.
真不想把你送走  米格尔
I am sorry to see you go, Miguel.
希望你早日魂归黄土
I hope you die very soon.
你知道我的意思
You know what I mean.
米格尔  我把祝福送给你
Miguel, I give you my bless...
我们说好的  孩子
We had a deal, chamaco.
你是谁  这是什么意思
Who are you? What is the meaning of this?
弗里达  我还以为你来不来了
Oh, Frida! I thought you couldn't make it.
你说会帮我把照片带回去
You said you'd take back my photo.
你答应过我的  米格尔
You promised, Miguel.
你认识这个  男人吗
You know this, uh, man?
今晚刚认识的  他说他认识你
Uh, I just met him tonight. He told me he knew you.
埃克托
Hector?
求你了  米格尔  把我的照片放上灵台
Please, Miguel. Put my photo up.
我的朋友  你被遗忘了
My friend, you're being forgotten.
-这又是谁的错  -埃克托  别这样
- And whose fault is that? - Hector, please...
你拿了我的歌  是我的歌让你出了名
Those were my songs you took. My songs that made you famous.
-什么  -我被遗忘了
- What? - If I'm being forgotten,
就是因为你没告诉大家歌是我写的
it's because you never told anyone that I wrote them!
这不可能  德拉库斯的歌是他自己写的
That's crazy! De la Cruz wrote all his own songs.
你要自己告诉他真相还是我来说
You want to tell him or should I?
埃克托  我从没抢你功劳的意思
Hector, I never meant to take credit.
我们曾是好拍档  可你死了
We made a great team, but you died...
我唱你的歌
and I only sang your songs
是因为我希望你的生命能以这种方式延续
because I wanted to keep a part of you alive.
真是太高尚了
Oh, how generous!
你们以前真的是搭档
You really did play together.
我不想再跟你计较这些了
I don't want to fight about it.
我只希望你能做出弥补
I just want you to make it right.
让米格尔把我的照片放上灵台  我就能走过花瓣桥
Miguel can put my photo up, and I can cross over the bridge.
去看我的女儿
I can see my girl.
埃内斯托  记得我离开那晚吗
Ernesto, remember the night I left?
那是很久前的事了
That was a long time ago.
我们一起喝酒  你告诉我
We drank together and you told me
你愿意为我赴汤蹈火  你说我是你的朋友
you would move Heaven and Earth... for your amigo.
我希望你能帮帮我
Well, I'm asking you to now.
赴汤蹈火  就像电影里说的
Heaven and Earth? Like in the movie?
-什么  -那是德拉库斯的电影
- What? - That's Don Hidalgo's toast.
《回家路上》里希达戈先生的祝酒词
In the De la Cruz movie, El Camino a Casa.
我说的是我身上发生的真事  米格尔
I'm talking about my real life, Miguel.
不  电影里也有  看
No! It's in there. Look!
没有比这更真切的语言了
Never were true words spoken.
这值得敬一杯  敬我们的友谊
This calls for a toast. To our friendship!
我愿为你赴汤蹈火  我的朋友
I would move Heaven and Earth for you, mi amigo.
但在电影里  希达戈先生在酒里下了毒
But in the movie, Don Hidalgo poisons the drink.
-干杯  -有毒
- Salud! - Poison!
那天晚上  埃内斯托  我死的那天晚...
That night, Ernesto. The night I left...
我们已经一路演出了好几个月
We'd been performing on the road for months.
我突然很想家
I got homesick...
于是收拾了东西
and I packed up my songs.
我们就快实现梦想了
You want to give up now
你却想现在一走了之
when we're this close to reaching our dream?
那是你的梦想  你自己去追
This was your dream. You'll manage.
没有你歌  我做不到  埃克托
I can't do this without your songs, Hector.
我要回家了  安室透
I'm going home, Ernesto.
你想恨我就恨吧  我已经下定决心了
Hate me if you want, but my mind is made up.
我怎么会恨你
Oh, I could never hate you.
你坚持要走  那我就敬一杯为你送行
If you must go, then I'm sending you off with a toast.
敬我们的友谊
To our friendship.
我愿为你赴汤蹈火  我的朋友  干杯
I would move Heaven and Earth for you, mi amigo. Salud!
你送我去车站
You walked me to the train station.
我突然觉得腹中一阵绞痛
But I felt a pain in my stomach.
我以为是我吃了不该吃的东西
I thought it must have been something I ate.
也许是熏香肠坏了  我的朋友
Perhaps it was that chorizo, my friend.
原来是喝了不该喝的
Or something I drank.
我就这样死了
I woke up dead.
你给我的酒里下毒
You poisoned me.
你把电影和现实搞混了  埃克托
You're confusing movies with reality, Hector.
这么久以来  我都觉得是我运气不好
All this time, I thought it was just bad luck.
从没想过是你  是你...
I never thought that you might have... That you...
《请记住我》
-你怎么可以这样  -埃克托
- How could you? - Hector!
来人啊  保安
Security! Security!
你夺走了我的一切  你这个小人
You took everything away from me! You rat!
妥善处理他  他有病
Have him taken care of. He's not well.
我只是想要回家  不  不
I just wanted to go back home. No! No!
真抱歉  我们刚才说到哪儿了
I apologize. Where were we?
你正准备把祝福送给我
You were going to give me your blessing.
对  没错
Yes. Uh, si.
米格尔  我的名声
Miguel, uh, my reputation...
对我来说非常重要
It is very important to me.
我不想让你以为...
I would hate to have you think...
你为了偷埃克托的歌  谋杀了他
That you murdered Hector for his songs?
你不会这么想吧  对吗
You don't think that. Do you?
我...当然不会了  人人都知道你是个好人
I... No. Everyone knows you're the good guy.
埃内斯托曾曾爷爷  我的祝福呢
Papa Ernesto, my blessing?
保安  看好米格尔  他回不去了
Security? Take care of Miguel. He'll be extending his stay.
什么  可我是你的家人
What? But I'm your family!
埃克托以前是我最好的朋友
And Hector was my best friend.
成功不是白来的  米格尔
Success doesn't come for free, Miguel.
你必须不择手段
You have to be willing to do whatever it takes
来抓住你的机遇
to seize your moment.
你会明白的
I know you understand.
不  不
No! No!
放开我  不
Let go! No!
救命  有人吗
Help! Can anyone hear me?
我想回家
I want to go home.
-埃克托  -孩子
- Hector? - Kid?
埃克托  你说得对
Oh, Hector! You were right.
我早该回到家人身边的
I should have gone back to my family.
他们让我不要像德拉库斯一样
They told me not to be like De la Cruz,
可我就是不听
but I didn't listen.
我还说我不在乎他们记不记得我
I told them I didn't care if they remembered me.
我说我不在乎我能不能被放上灵台
I didn't care if I was on their stupid ofrenda.
孩子  没关系  没事的
Hey, chamaco. It's okay. It's okay.
我说我不在乎
I told them I didn't care.
埃克托  埃克托
Hector! Hector?
她快把我忘了
She's forgetting me.
-谁  -我的女儿
- Who? - My daughter.
你想过桥就是为了去见她
She's the reason you wanted to cross the bridge.
我只想再看看她
I just wanted to see her again.
我不该离开圣塞西莉亚
I never should have left Santa Cecilia.
我多想跟她说声对不起
I wish I could apologize.
多想告诉她爸爸本来是要回家了
I wish I could tell her that her papa was trying to come home.
告诉她爸爸非常爱她
That he loved her so much.
我的可可
My Coco...
可可
Coco?
这是从哪儿来的
Where did you get this?
这是我的曾奶奶可可  这是我的曾曾奶奶伊美黛
That's my Mama Coco. That's my Mama Imelda.
这是你吗
Is that you?
-我们是...一家人  -一家人
- We're...Family? - Family?
我一直希望还能再见到她
I always hoped I'd see her again.
希望她也想我
That she'd miss me.
她会把我的照片放上灵坛  可是从来没有
Maybe put up my photo. But it never happened.
你知道最让我难过的是什么吗
You know the worst part?
我以为就算我不能去活人世界见我的可可
Even if I never got to see Coco in the living world...
总有一天我会在这里见到她
I thought at least one day I'd see her here.
我会给她一个大大的拥抱
Give her the biggest hug.
可是她是活人世界里最后一个记得我的人
But she's the last person who remembers me.
一旦她离开了活人的世界...
The moment she's gone from the living world...
你就  从这里消失了
You disappear... from this one.
你再也见不到她了
You'll never get to see her.
再也见不到了
Ever again.
知道吗  我给她写过一首歌
You know, I wrote her a song once.
以前我们每天晚上都会一起唱
We used to sing it every night at the same time.
不管离家多远我都会唱
No matter how far apart we were.
我好想再为她唱一回
What I wouldn't give to sing it to her
就  最后  一回
one... last... time.
请记住我
Remember me
虽然再见必须说
Though I have to say goodbye
请记住我
Remember me
眼泪不要坠落
Don't let it make you cry
我虽然要离你远去
For even if I'm far away
你住在我心底
I hold you in my heart
在每个分离的夜里
I sing a secret song to you
为你唱一首歌
Each night we are apart
请记住我
Remember me
爸爸
Papa!
虽然我要去远方
Though I have to travel far
请记住我
Remember me
当听见吉他的悲伤
Each time you hear a sad guitar
这就是我跟你在一起唯一的凭据
Know that I'm with you the only way that I can be
直到我再次拥抱你
Until you're in my arms again
请记住我
Remember me
他偷走了你的吉他  还偷了你的歌
He stole your guitar. He stole your songs.
被世人铭记的人应该是你  不是德拉库斯
You should be the one the world remembers, not De la Cruz!
这首歌不是写给别人听的
I didn't write Remember Me for the world.
是写给我的可可的
I wrote it for Coco.
作为你的曾曾爷爷我真的不够格
I'm a pretty sorry excuse for a great-great-grandpa.
你在开玩笑吗
Are you kidding?
我刚刚还以为我的曾曾爷爷是个杀人犯
A minute ago I thought I was related to a murderer.
你可比他好太多了
You're a total upgrade.
从小到大  我都觉得
My whole life, there's been something...
我跟家里人不太一样
that made me different.
我从不知道为何如此
And I never knew where it came from.
现在我知道了  是因为你
But now I know. It comes from you.
太好了我们是一家人  太好了我们是一家人
I'm proud we're family! I'm proud to be his family!
太好了我们是一家人
I'm proud to be his family!
但丁
Dante?
Dante!
是但丁
It's Dante!
-伊美黛  -埃克托
- Imelda! - Hector.
你气色不错
You look good.
但丁  你一直知道埃克托是我的曾曾爷爷
Dante! You knew he was my Papa Hector the whole time!
你是真的灵魂向导
You are a real spirit guide.
谁是最棒的灵魂向导  是你
Who's the good spirit guide? You are!
但丁
Dante!
他们回来了
There they are!
米格尔  小米格尔
Miguel! Miguelito!
看  是米格尔  他没事
Look, it's Miguel! He's all right.
太好了  谢天谢地
Que bueno. Gracias, Dios mio.
亲爱的  我担心死了
Mijo, I was so worried!
谢天谢地我们及时找到你了
Thank goodness we found you in time.
至于你  我告诉你多少次了我不想见你
And you... How many times must I turn you away?
伊美黛
Imelda.
我不想跟你有任何关系  活着不想  死了也一样
I want nothing to do with you! Not in life, not in death!
我花了数十年让家人远离你犯的错
I spent decades protecting my family from your mistakes.
他才跟你在一起五分钟
He spends five minutes with you
就被扔进了一个天坑里
and I have to fish him out of a sinkhole!
我被扔进天坑不是因为埃克托
I wasn't in there because of Hector.
反倒是他被我牵连
He was in there because of me.
他想帮我回家
He was just trying to get me home!
我不肯听他的  他说得对
I didn't want to listen, but he was right.
没有什么比家人更重要
Nothing's more important than family.
我准备好接受您的祝福了
I'm ready to accept your blessing.
还有您的所有条件
And your conditions.
但首先  我得找到德拉库斯
But first, I need to find De la Cruz.
拿回埃克托的照片
To get Hector's photo.
-什么  -这样他才能再见到可可
- What? - So he can see Coco again.
家里的灵坛上应该有他
Hector should be on our ofrenda.
他也是我们的家人
He's part of our family.
他离开了这个家
He left this family!
他本来想回来找你和可可的
He tried to go home to you and Coco.
可德拉库斯害死了他
But De la Cruz murdered him!
是真的  伊美黛
It's true, Imelda.
是真的又怎么样
And so what if it's true?
你当初扔下我一个人抚养孩子
You leave me alone with a child to raise...
我就该这么原谅你吗
and I'm just supposed to forgive you?
伊美黛  我...
Imelda, I...
埃克托
Hector!
我快没时间了  是可可
I'm running out of time. It's Coco.
她快把你忘了
She's forgetting you.
你不必原谅他
You don't have to forgive him.
但我们不该忘了他
But we shouldn't forget him.
我想忘掉你
I wanted to forget you.
我还想让可可也把你忘掉  可是...
I wanted Coco to forget you too, but...
这是我的错  不怪你
This is my fault. Not yours.
对不起  伊美黛
I'm sorry, Imelda.
米格尔  我们帮你拿回他的照片
Miguel, if we help you get his photo,
你就乖乖回家
you will return home?
再也不碰音乐
No more music?
家人最重要
Family comes first.
我没法原谅你
I can't forgive you.
但我会帮助你
But I will help you.
我们要怎么接近德拉库斯
So, how do we get to De la Cruz?
我可能知道个办法
I might know a way.
-祝你好运  孩子  -谢谢你  弗里达
- Good luck, muchacho. - Gracias, Frida.
-来  我帮你  -别碰我
- Here, let me help you with... - Don't touch me!
-大家都清楚计划了吗  -找到埃克托的照片
- Everyone clear on the plan? - Find Hector's photo.
-拿给米格尔  -送米格尔回家
- Give it to Miguel. - Send Miguel home.
都有花瓣吗
Got your petals?
现在我们只要找到德拉库斯
Now, we just have to find De la Cruz.
谁找我
Yes?
我认识你吗
Don't I know you?
这一巴掌是因为你谋杀了我最爱的人
That's for murdering the love of my life!
-谁  你说谁  -她说的是我
- Who... Who the... - She's talking about me!
我是你最爱的人吗
I'm the love of your life?
我不知道  我还生气着呢
I don't know. I'm still angry at you.
埃克托  你是怎么...
Hector! How did you...
这一巴掌是因为你意图谋杀我的曾曾孙子
And that's for trying to murder my grandson.
-曾曾孙子  -她说的是我
- Grandson? - She's talking about me!
你  慢着  你是埃克托是一家人
You! Wait. You're related to Hector?
照片
The photo!
抓住他
After him!
保安  快保护我
Security! Ayudenme!
-你说我是你最爱的人  -我不知道我说了什么
- You said love of your life. - I don't know what I said.
我听到你说了
That's what I heard.
请就位  先生  三十秒后登台
Places, Senor. You're on in thirty seconds.
米格尔  我拿到了
Miguel! I have it!
快  快点
Hurry! Come on!
女士们  先生们
Ladies and gentlemen...
欢迎举世无双的歌神
the one... the only...
埃内斯托·德拉库斯
Ernesto De la Cruz!
把她给我抓下来
Get her off the stage.
唱  唱
Sing! Sing!
可怜的我
Ay, de mí Llorona
天蓝色的  哭泣的女人
Llorona de azul celeste
可怜的我
Ay, de mí Llorona
天蓝色的  哭泣的女人
Llorona de azul celeste
虽然生活对我百般折磨  哭泣的女人
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
我也不会停止爱你
No dejaré de quererte
我爬上那最高的松
Me subí al pino más alto, Llorona
是为了看到你
A ver si te divisaba
像那松树一样容易流泪  哭泣的女人
Como el pino era tierno, Llorona
看到我在流泪了吧
Al verme llorar, lloraba
可怜的我  流泪的女人
Ay, de mí Llorona, Llorona
天蓝色的  哭泣的女人
Llorona de azul celeste
可怜的我  哭泣的女人
Ay, de mí Llorona, Llorona
天蓝色的  哭泣的女人
Llorona de azul celeste
虽然生活对我百般折磨  哭泣的女人
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
我也不会停止爱你
No dejaré de quererte
虽然生活对我百般折磨  哭泣的女人
Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona
放开我
Let go of me!
我也不会停止爱你
No dejaré de quererte
我快忘记唱歌的感觉了
I forgot what that felt like.
你还是唱得很好
You still got it.
米格尔  我给你我的祝福
Miguel, I give you my blessing.
送你回家  把我们的照片放上灵坛
To go home, to put up our photos
永远
and to never...
永远别碰音乐
Never play music again.
永远记住你的家人有多么爱你
To never forget how much your family loves you.
回家吧
You're going home.
你哪儿也不许去
You're not going anywhere.
伊美黛
Imelda!
退后  退后
Stay back! Stay back!
你们都给我退后  别再过来了
All of you, stay back. Not one more step.
但丁
Dante!
埃内斯托  住手  放开那孩子
Ernesto, stop! Leave the boy alone.
我付出了这么多  埃克托
I've worked too hard, Hector.
我不能让他毁了我的一切
Too hard to let him destroy everything.
这孩子还活着  埃内斯托
He's a living child, Ernesto.
他是个威胁
He's a threat!
你觉得我会让他
You think I'd let him go back
带着你的照片回到活人的世界吗
to the Land of the Living with your photo?
让世人都记起你吗  不
To keep your memory alive? No.
-你这个懦夫  -我是埃内斯托·德拉库斯
- You're a coward! - I am Ernesto De la Cruz.
世上最伟大的音乐家
The greatest musician of all time!
埃克托才是最伟大的音乐家
Hector's the real musician.
是你谋杀了他  偷走了他的歌
You're just the guy who murdered him and stole his songs!
谋杀
Murdered?
我只是用尽办法
I am the one who's willing to do
抓住我的机遇
what it takes to seize my moment.
不惜一切代价
Whatever it takes.
不
No!
-米格尔  -米格尔
- Miguel! - Miguel!
对不起了  老朋友  演出还得继续
Apologies, old friend. But the show must go on.
抱歉  抱歉  我的家人们
Please, please, mi familia.
杀人犯
Murderer!
乐队准备  1  2  1
Orchestra. A-one, a-two, a-one...
请记住我
Remember me
虽然再见...
Though I have to s...
看
Look!
乖猫咪
Nice kitty.
放我下来  不  求求你
Put me down! No, please!
求求你  停下  快停下  不
I beg of you! Stop! Stop! No!
不  不
No! No!
我错过了什么
What did I miss?
真棒  但丁
Good boy, Dante!
米格尔
Miguel!
埃克托  照片...掉了
Hector! The photo... I lost it!
没关系  亲爱的  没关...
It's okay, mijo. It's o...
埃克托  埃克托
Hector! Hector?
可可
Coco.
不  我们可以把照片找回来
No! We can still find the photo.
米格尔  太阳就快升起了
Miguel, it's almost sunrise.
不  不  我还不能走
No, no. I can't leave you.
我答应要把你的照片放到灵坛上
I promised I'd put your photo up.
让你再见到可可曾奶奶
I promised you'd see Coco.
我们都快没时间了
We're both out of time, mijo.
不  不  她不能忘了你
Oh no! No! She can't forget you!
我只希望她知道我爱她
I just wanted her to know that I loved her.
埃克托
Hector!
我们把祝福送给你  米格尔
You have our blessing, Miguel.
没有任何条件
No conditions.
不  埃克托曾曾爷爷  求求你
No! Papa Hector, please!
不
No!
回家去
Go home.
我发誓不会让可可曾奶奶忘记你
I promise I won't let Coco forget you!
他在那里
There he is!
米格尔  等等
Miguel! Stop!
你去哪里了
Where have you been?
我得去找可可曾奶奶  求求你
I need to see Mama Coco, please.
你拿着那个干什么  给我
What are you doing with that... Give it to me!
米格尔  站住  米格尔  米格尔
Miguel, stop! Miguel! Miguel!
可可曾奶奶  你能听到吗  我是米格尔
Mama Coco? Can you hear me? It's Miguel.
我见到你爸爸了  记得吗  爸爸
I saw your papa. Remember? Papa?
求求你  要是你也把他忘了  他就会消失了
Please! If you forget him, he'll be gone.
永远消失
Forever.
米格尔  把门打开
Miguel, open this door!
看  这是他的吉他  对吗
Here. This was his guitar, right?
他以前总弹给您听
He used to play it to you?
看  这个是他  爸爸
See? There he is! Papa!
记得吗  爸爸
Remember? Papa?
米格尔
Miguel!
可可曾奶奶  求求你  不要把他忘了
Mama Coco, please! Don't forget him.
你缠着你曾奶奶在干什么
What are you doing to that poor woman?
没事的  妈  没事的
It's okay, Mamita. It's okay.
你怎么回事
What's gotten into you?
我以为你再也回不来了  米格尔
I thought I'd lost you, Miguel.
对不起  爸爸
I'm sorry, Papa.
我们一家人又在一起了  这才是最重要的
We're all together now. That's what matters.
还缺一个人
Not all of us.
没事了  妈妈
It's okay, Mamita.
米格尔  给你可可曾奶奶道个歉
Miguel, you apologize to your Mama Coco.
可可曾奶奶
Mama Coco?
快点道歉
Well? Apologize!
可可曾奶奶
Mama Coco?
你的爸爸  想让您再听听这首歌
Your papa, he wanted you to have this.
妈妈  等等
Mama, wait!
请记住我
Remember me
虽然再见必须说
Though I have to say goodbye
请记住我
Remember me
眼泪不要坠落
Don't let it make you cry
我虽然要离你远去
For even if I'm far away
你住在我心底
I hold you in my heart
在每个分离的夜里
I sing a secret song to you
为你唱一首歌
Each night we are apart
请记住我
Remember me
虽然我要去远方
Though I have to travel far
请记住我
Remember me
当听见吉他的悲伤
Each time you hear a sad guitar
这就是我跟你在一起唯一的凭据
Know that I'm with you the only way that I can be
直到我再次拥抱你
Until you're in my arms again
请记住我
Remember me
埃琳娜  你怎么了  亲爱的
Elena? What's wrong, mija?
没事  妈妈  我没事
Nothing, Mama. Nothing at all.
我爸爸以前总会给我唱这首歌
My papa used to sing me that song.
他很爱你  可可曾奶奶
He loved you, Mama Coco.
你的爸爸非常非常爱你
Your papa loved you so much.
我还留着他写来的信
I kept his letters.
里面有他给我写的诗  还有这个
Poems he wrote me. And...
爸爸是个音乐家
Papa was a musician.
我小的时候
When I was a little girl...
他和妈妈总一起唱好听的歌
he and Mama would sing such beautiful songs.
一年后
请记住我
鬼才记得你
这一边
And right over here,
是圣塞西莉亚伟大的文化瑰宝之一
one of Santa Cecilia's greatest treasures.
尊敬的歌曲家埃克托·里维拉的故居
The home of the esteemed song writer, Hector Rivera.
在他写给女儿可可的家书中
The letters Hector wrote home for his daughter, Coco,
蕴藏着很多脍炙人口的歌词
contain the lyrics for all of your favorite songs.
不仅仅是《请记住我》
Not just Remember Me.
这是胡里奥曾爷爷
And that man is your Papa Julio.
这是罗西塔姑婆和维多利亚姨婆
And there's Tia Rosita and your Tia Victoria.
这是奥斯卡和菲利普叔公
And those two are Oscar and Felipe.
这些照片里的人都是我们的家人
These aren't just old pictures, they're our family...
我们永远不能忘记他们
and they're counting on us to remember them.
-你叫我疯子  我傻得可以  -下一位
- Say that I'm crazy or call me a fool - Next!
探亲愉快  埃克托
Enjoy your visit, Hector.
但昨夜梦里我仿佛看见你
But last night it seemed that I dreamed about you
-爸爸  -可可
- Papa! - Coco!
当我开口要说
When I opened my mouth
言语变一首歌
what came out was a song
每一句都熟悉
And you know every word
我们来一起唱
and we all sang along
旋律美丽响起
To a melody played
灵魂在音符里
on the strings of our souls
我们身体摆动着跟音乐节奏
And a rhythm that rattled us down to the bone
我们相亲相爱  生命不灭不息
Our love for each other will live on forever
我的心跳全都充满自豪
In every beat of my proud corazon
我们相亲相爱  生命不灭不息
Our love for each other will live on forever
我的心跳全都充满自豪
In every beat of my proud corazon
我的大家庭  我的好朋友
Ay mi familia Oiga mi gente
你可感觉到  你可知道
Canten a coro Let it be known
我们相亲相爱  生命不灭不息
Our love for each other will live on forever
我的心跳全都充满自豪
In every beat of my proud corazon
我的大家庭  我的好朋友
Ay mi familia Oiga mi gente
你可感觉到  你可知道
Canten a coro Let it be known
我们相亲相爱  生命不灭不息
Our love for each other will live on forever
我的心跳全都充满自豪
In every beat of my proud corazon